[Music]
um hi nice to meet you um really really
honored to be speaking for you all today
about such an exciting topic as AI power
development now you are listening to
pre-recording which we made just in case
that I would give birth before the
actual conference so if you're watching
this that actually happen and then maybe
I see you in real life in the Q&A with
my baby good um so let me bring up my
slides today I want to uh inspire you
and show you a couple of tools that you
can start using today to uh code with AI
faster let's Dive Right In with some
inspirational examples
so chat GPT I think everybody has heard
of it and probably already used either
chat GPT or CLA or or something else I
would just wanted to uh point you to
some use cases that for us software
development uh developers are really
interesting so uh what I'm going to do
is I'm going to show you this and
instead of typing all my queries I'm G
to copy them in so you don't have to see
me typing slow and making mistakes so my
first question uh I come from from a
bioinformatics background so in drug
development which is a really exciting
field by the way um going to ask it this
give me 10 lab result values measured by
a lab physician while developing
biologic drugs in Json format and as you
can see this is indeed nice Json format
and what I actually did right now is
create myself a set of test data that is
uh nonproprietary that is not protected
because with real clinical data
typically there's a lot of issues in
actually getting the data or being
allowed to use them or show them um and
tgpt did a great job like imagine I had
to type this all out I'm happy I don't
have to do that now maybe I want to
enter all this data in a little front
end um to then store it in my back end
so since I'm a backend developer a Java
developer as you may maybe see
throughout the rest of the presentation
a bit uh I'm really bad at front end so
I'm just going to ask that GPT to make
me an HTML page where the physician can
enter protein identifier which is the
name of the molecule and uh all this
data from above in a web form and upon
clicking submit to send the data to the
back end at local
host and give the user an uploaded
successfully message and then
interestingly I'm asking one HTML file
only with CSS and JavaScript integrated
because we never know where to put the
files to so they're actually found being
very lazy here um so let's see if we are
already at the end of this exactly the
closing tag so this should be a complete
HTML page now I have this little
renderer here where I paste this HTML in
oops and what we can see is that we have
that's an
interesting an interesting thing without
a title um so I have the protein protein
identifier that I asked for and then if
I'm going to just put in some Tommy
value and
submit okay I get um please fill in this
field so it made all Fields mandatory I
hadn't specified it so I can go back uh
back and forth at some colors at a title
uh whatever but this is actually
functional HTML code uh that cost me
really like 30 seconds to
generate um another example of why AI is
so nice um when I give presentation live
I tend to ask who of you in the audience
likes to parse around with date time
formats and time zones and then
typically that's only some funny guys
raising their hand because I think we
all hate it um I'm going to show you an
example with Lang chain for J because
I'm one of the collaborators on the
framework but I mean this can be done in
Python with Lang chain and csharp with
semantic kernel so there's these days
Frameworks uh for every possible
programming language um so let's see how
we can circumvent this with Lang chain
for J in Java so we're looking at this
piece of code and um let me wipe no let
me not wipe yes let me wipe this was a
surprise um so we first want to set up a
connection to a model and in our case
we're going to use an open AI chat model
we're going to set our key we pick GPT 4
and that's it we build this and Lang
chain for J then we actually have access
to gp4 over
API then what uh Lang chain forj allows
you to do is build what we call AI
Services um you declare what you want to
happen instead of typically in coding we
uh specify algorithmically what has to
happen um with AI Services we can just
say we want a class text details with a
method exct extract data time from a
text
and we want a local data time object the
Java object to be returned apart from
that we're not doing anything yet and
we're going to uh tweak this in a bit by
specifying a user message for the model
that says extract date and time from it
being this
text now if we want to use this class
for real we can just say AI services.
create from this text dils class and we
specify the model it has to go to to
actually get this fixed to get this
working um so as you can see I'm not
writing any real code so far and now I
can already use this text dils do
extract daytime from and we're going to
do this from this text here three days
before s Valentine's Day of 2024 just 15
minutes shy of midnight Jane discovered
that Jim was more in love with his IDE
than with her this happens right
especially now with all these cool AI
tools this really does happen um and we
want this local daytime object back so
let's run that and see we're going to
then print the
object there we go so we have indeed 15
minute shy of midnight um then uh 11th
of February so that's uh 14 13 12 11
it's correct it's three days before St
Valentine's Day uh super nice we didn't
have to par this this date object uh I
do want you to know that it's not always
going to be correct like depending on
the you're using you're going to be like
95% correct it can make mistakes it
stays AI after
all another use case is where AI can um
translate natural language to SQL
scripts even if I do like to write SQL
there are a number of applications where
it's really nice when AI can do it for
you um so what I want to show there is a
little again a Java program again using
L for J and quarcus uh we have a little
chatbot here uh so I have it up and
running already and I'm gonna ask it
it's a mie movie Muse that will help me
pick my movie so I
want H let's forget about um typing
mistakes I want to watch
a fantasy movie from the
80s um so nice I don't have to select
stuff I can just ask my question and I
get
yay stor War the Empire stries back in
1980 interesting so how did it find this
well it couldn't know it right but what
we do have is a movie database in the
background so that's has been running
here and um this is the SQL query that
this llm has generated from my question
so select the movie name and some more
stuff from the movie table where the
genre is like fantasy and the year of
release is between 1980 and 19 89 and
that's how it found it and it orders it
by um by
rating so uh that was just really good
uh AI is actually really good at doing
this kind of
stuff now um I want you to start
thinking meta for the rest of this
presentation and also afterwards so llms
they're good but they sometimes make
mistakes and then there's actually ways
to remediate that so LMS can write code
that's going to be sometimes a bit buggy
they can also write unit tests they will
also be a bit buggy but then if you pair
them you will find what's wrong in both
of them very fast and you will actually
have gained a lot of time um llms can
score and rank their own Solutions it's
sometimes wor to have them rethink them
they can also generate steps and then
have either other llms or specialized
models execute all the steps and they
can even decide whether a task is
actually suitable for an llm or not
and then with regard to that uh you see
here a little schematic of what we call
Advanced rag rag retrieval augmented
generation is a way to um help llms know
your context of your documents things
they were not trained on WE we'll we'll
take pieces of your documentation that
are relevant to the question and we will
send them along to the llm so it will
know will be able to answer in a much
better way based on your specific
documents now the basic rag only uses
semantic search so it goes find pieces
of text in your documents but sometimes
we have also data that is stored in
databases or sometimes you need to go
look on the web if it's something that
just came out maybe we will not have it
in our documents it will not be in a
training data set then it would be
interesting if the llm could go search
on the web and so where this llm uh
comes in would be in the query router
where it can decide like ah for this
question should I go look in my
documents or in my database it knows the
scheme if you pass it to the llm or
should I go look this up on the web and
actually can choose very well or does a
combination and then it also translate
this question into a good question for
web search or into a SQL query as we
just saw or into a good query for this
semantic search
version all right so these were just
some inspirational examples um now today
what I want to show you is how does AI
actually work going to be very quick
because I think you know more or less um
how it can help with software
development some things to watch out for
though and then a short future outlook
to know if we are out of a job or not so
let's Dive Right In so I'm liisa Ras I
work at nabo doai for a short while I'm
going to show that to a bit later on
because it perfectly fits in the talk
and um I'm also a collaborator of the
Lang chain forj framework from the first
hour um that's why also a lot of
examples you will see will be in langing
for
Java so how AI actually works I'm just
gonna give you this one which I like a
lot it's showing um visual class image
classification so you see how the pixels
are entered in layer one and then they
move throughout this neural network um
how much from one node goes to a next
node depends on the weights there um so
if you look just at the architecture you
have this neural network if you have the
weights you train this with a lot of
data and then you can obtain all the
weights here then you are speaking about
the model so trained neural network and
then classifies it like this now that
was the easy simple version for demo in
reality image classification looks more
like this with a lot of layers with a
lot of parallel calculations that
require
to use uh typically optimized Hardware
gpus or some some newer version of them
that can do this massive amount of
parallel calculations and what's
important for developers to keep in mind
is that like input can be anything that
you can digitalize so it can be text and
images as we know it but it can be heat
Maps it can be really anything um and
then the model is just a calculation
scheme so in itself it's not a security
risk the security or data privacy risk
comes when you use it as a software as a
service from a provider uh they can do
the stuff with your data around it but
the model itself is just calculating and
passing through and then again the
output can be anything again like a
label in this case or the next word or
even depth estimates so there's also a
lot of um applications to build around
different kind of models so that's one
of the reasons I don't think we're out
of a job
soon um now now we work we know a bit
how it works um how can it help us in
this software development life cycle so
here it is one of the versions of it and
I'm going to first see how they how AI
can help in every step of this life
cycle and then I'm going to have a look
at tools that operate over the entire
life cycle so starting with analysis and
scope I hear a lot of people saying like
oh we are not out of a job yet as
Developers because our customers don't
even know themselves what they want they
really need our help um and I think
that's wrong I think that's exactly
where AI can help so much I have tried
on chbt to behave like a customer that
has no clue what he wants and if CPT
knows that it has to help me get decent
technical specifications out it does a
marvelous job at guiding me at asking me
about my edge cases what do you want in
this case would you want this and that
so honestly it's maybe one of the strong
cases for AI to help us with to get
these nice text specs and to get them
inversions for project management for
the Developers for the clients to sign
off then um exactly so then uh we go to
design and architecture so typically if
you have to decide on how to uh what the
architecture and tex stack of your app
is going to look like you need to know a
lot about all the most recent Frameworks
out there uh and how they compare in
specific points the nice thing is AI has
seen this all and in that sense it's a
really nice advisor that can help you uh
making better decisions also for
suggesting which dependencies I have to
use I'm using it all the time and again
to not forget about all these edge cases
it's really
marvelous then implementation and
documentation is probably the thing that
most people have already heard about or
have had their hands on most these
days um so I like this little prediction
of what the most popular programming
language is going to be in 2030 that
would be English followed by Mandarin
and so on um the way I see things
develop right now I think this might be
right like we will still have
programmers that actually uh know the
programming languages very well just as
today we still have people that know
assembly for example um they are still
needed but I think the majority of
people might well be programming in
English be it with comments um yeah then
they're very interested because things
are moving very very fast these days
now um most of you will have used
something like GitHub co-pilot or Intel
J AI assistant um there are nice for
boilerplate code right where you're
working but then we see that they
struggle when you have as questions that
go over classes that uh communicate with
other parts of the code and stuff so I
just want you to know that people are
working on making this better many
people um so they're adding like graph
rack approaches to this uh to get much
much better and much more more correct
answers so I think these coding
assistants are going to get much much
better in the coming
years um then you have like help in your
um IDE as well just mentioning Devo
Jenny here because um they allow you to
also pick local models um to guide you
and help you write code uh there's a
nice thing for everybody that's working
in regulated environments and that's not
just allowed to use uh GitHub copilot
which goes to open AI or intelli
assistant which I'm not sure where they
go but like if you want to be sure um
your code and maybe your IP stays local
you can use this tool for
example um then there is cursor. comom
which is uh my personal favorite because
it does a lot of things right that other
things struggle with so uh I want to
show you a cursor in action so this is a
part of a little program I wrote It's a
feedback analyzer that uses AI to split
the user feedback that you can see here
in um topics that are on one topic so
this one is about examples but also
about room temperature so what it's
going to do when I click submit it's
going to split them one is about yeah
the examples one about the room
temperature and then it's going to
categorize and even say like okay impact
is 100% of the people in the room
probably but severity is only 10% um so
this is really nice because it comes
also with dashboard for the admin
afterwards where everything is
aggregated uh and we see how many urgent
problems and what what they are about
now um I'm going to use cursor because I
want to add for example a field
profession in here and therefore let's
go to cursor so it's a clone of vs code
I have my feedback analyzer loaded in
here and I want I'm just going to copy
my query so you don't have to see me
type again so I'm ask going to ask it
here and going to take the entire code
base to chat with not just the file I'm
looking at and that's that's the
important thing that's what cursor does
so nicely it sees your entire code base
and then it gives you really smart
Solutions not just something that works
maybe in one file um I've asked so that
I want to add this field profession
right after gender and I want to use
this profession value throughout the
rest of the app just like gender is used
further on make sure to give your
answers in apply div format that's my
little trick if you ask for apply div
gets really easy and what cursor does so
nicely it finds not just one file but it
finds like all the files it has to
change um so let's go here and feedback.
HTML and apply the div so here I get um
profession edit G to accept that the
next one seems to also be in
here
um there we go so it's sh that doesn't
look great let's skip this like so you
always have to check yourself typically
this is not happen I'm going to reject
this one because it really not looking
good uh then in my feedback data
transfer object I of course need it as
well so it adds it here it gives me a
getter and a Setter lovely and so on and
so on in my Java object then it adds it
as well super nice in my two string
method like so I love this I must say
that when I start a new file um one
thing you have to know is set up your
file structure correctly but then you
can really let cursor write all your
code SQL HTML Java python it does a
great job um also when you want to like
add a big functionality to something
existing I can really recommend this one
and then I typically go back to my
intelligy because I work faster in
it um good that was curser um maybe some
of you heard of um software agents like
Devon um so as you can see Devon at some
point scored around 14% I think this was
uh upwork tasks so real coding tasks
that get actually paid and dein was able
to solve a part of it I just want you to
know there's also an open source version
this software um engineering agent from
Princeton that you can find here now
that was already over a year ago these
numbers uh in the meantime this are
Devon's own benchmarks so it's going
getting better and better with also this
o1 mini from chat GPT um it's worth to
have a look on YouTube how these things
actually work because it's basically an
llm or a code model that also can has
tools to scroll in your code to go to
certain files to make changes to compile
it to look at the the error messages
like very much like we would also solve
it good then repet is also a new tool
that came out there was a lot of Buzz
that works really well uh so I tried it
out and I asked like for my next demo I
need a shopping assistant can you write
it for me in a Java uh with the HTML
front end simply I said like oh no I
only do uh JavaScript and python I was
like ah so I hope they add some more
languages later on then I tried it out
with the python version um well if you
have like a standard application like a
web shop it even proposed me shall I do
user authentication and credit card
validation and I was like yes great
because I don't really know how to do
this that's amazing um so far great for
repet but then when I start saying oh I
wanted to tweak it a bit I want actually
an AI model to be called in the back to
choose what's going to pop up here in
the product suggestions and everything
it started failing and we got in a loop
where it was a whole mess um but for for
for basic programs this is really nice
so do test it out you know takes a bit
of time to generate it uh and it will
also render the thing and ask you is it
working now can you click on the button
can you give me feedback what is working
what is not working and based on that I
will rework the
code um some other tools you can use uh
code rabbit AI is something for your
GitHub uh pool requests that will um
review the P requests and also make
suggestions for fixes with an apply diff
sometimes which is really nice so I can
recommend using this um typically I find
some bugs or code flavors that I don't
like but then code rabbit finds some
other things that I overlooked and I
think as a combo we we do better job
than me
alone there's also doot uh that one will
review issues so when the issue on
GitHub has not been answered within a
certain time frame doot comes in and it
will suggest um how to fix this or how
to add this and um this was an example
from our length chain for
repository um and somebody from Google
told me it was about the vertex AI gmin
integration he said this suggestion was
actually really non-trivial and really
good it has put us on the track to
actually solve this issue so that's
another one I can really
recommend uh then when it comes to
documentation I didn't find the tool yet
I'm really happy to hear it from you so
like reach out if you know Cool Tools uh
and let me know um documentation is like
it's it's annoying to write it's very
annoying to go read in and then very
often you don't even find what you
wanted to know in it I know and then
when you update your code you forget to
update the documentation I know and I
just also know that AI is in the perfect
spot to make all of these steps easier
to automatically generated to know when
it should be updated based on the code
you update and to help you interact with
this documentation when you just would
have a chat bot to ask how to do it and
it will find the right parts right away
for you
um okay let's move on to testing so as I
already said generating unit test is
goes super fast it knows like which edge
cases to cover it's not going to be
perfect these tests but they will fail
if they were wrong so you will see it
nonetheless and you can fix them uh my
code is covered so much better since I'm
just using C GPT to cover to write my
unit tests because it catches much more
than I would think of uh also for
writing selenium tests where you like
you know what you want to happen but you
struggle with this horrible syntax
that's exactly where AI is super strong
and to generate synthetic uh test demo
uh test data there's actually whole
companies out there that build their
business model on on this synthetic test
data when it comes to the deployment it
people they have usually uh interact
with a lot of servers and configuration
files and every time a little bit
different again so also AI is really
helpful in assisting them
there um when we move on to then
maintenance there are already quite some
companies out there that are using AI to
automatically look at their log files
and see if there's security breaches or
just like bugs things not going well and
then report them the other part is that
once a bug is reported or a security
breach is reported um AI can
automatically dispatch this book in
theory to the right person already
pointed bit to the part of code where it
should uh be fixed again I'm really
curious to hear if people already have
tools that do this but I know it's
perfectly
possible um good now when we look at
this entire life cycle we can actually
also have ai help us over the whole life
cycle and this was a slide I was
presenting um before summer um where I
said like hey you can break all these
information silos by allowing to Joint
search on your text spec Gyra tickets
your code your book reports wouldn't
that be amazing instead of we going to
search everywhere and then somebody
comes to me and says like hey that's
exactly what we are building in nabo a
so now I'm working for them so I quickly
wanted to show just how nice this is um
let me
go so what nabo does so this is from our
own nabo G repository um it allows you
here with this little plugin to ask any
question you want and I'm going to just
ask how do I test this PR because like
it's a bit of mtpr as usual right and
what Nabu does is it looks really
through all the Integrations we have in
our company so Confluence Gyra GitHub
Google Docs and it goes find related
tickets uh and everything so it can
actually tell me how step by step I
should do the testing of this PR which
is super practical and I don't need to
leave uh my workflow at all or go find
these
documents um another one is when I use
the app here
so this is not within the context of
this this uh pull request I can ask um I
have uh someone
complaining that report generation in
CRM is not working so this kind of help
desk is this a known
issue um so instead of having to call
around as help desk person I can ask if
this issue has already been reported
then yes it's been reported there's the
bug report ticket it even finds a
workaround guide for me and there has
been a discussion that a hot fix is
being developed and now I can go look in
the workaround guide or I can say how
can I work around this for now like
being Ultra lazy instead of opening this
guide and this is where I love AI so
much so there you go it's like the
summary of what's in this document and
like the nice thing with Nabu if you
want to go check it's one one click away
and it opens you this thing in
Confluence good that's one way of
interacting over everything in this
cycle and making things faster um I will
also took a look at GitHub copilot
workspace I'm not sure if there're still
on a weight list or not as of today um
also it's pretends to help you with this
whole life cycle I tried it out and so
you have to know it only works on GitHub
only on your main branch where typically
you do want AI to change things that was
a bit annoying but the nice thing that
it does well is when you say I want to I
wanted to add a ordering uh
functionality to my work to my web shop
and the first thing it does like are
there already proper methods to store
the order products I like that because I
made some stops here and there where I
still had to come back to because it was
a Pock um it searched it for me and it
says like yeah there is a method save
order in shopping database already but
it assumes client ID and product ID are
one like yeah sounds like something I
would have done and then I just know
where to go fix it that part was really
nice but then it offered me a fix with
methods that just don't work and then I
said hey these methods don't work and
then he said like oh well I'm GNA add
them for you so they actually work
instead of looking at which methods were
already there and have a look I had an
order object with a client his address
uh list of items that he B buys and the
total price and it's in green is what um
getop pilot workspace edit a user ID
like yes I already had a client name a
product name I already had a whole list
of products right and a quantity which
is like yeah sorry this is a bit too
stupid I'm not going to deal with the
booking this kind of stuff I'm going to
come back to this toool in half a year
and see if it got
better right um what should we watch out
for uh um
so climate wise AI is not the best thing
it's ask a lot of compute power but I
want you to know that it does the models
do get smaller and the quality goes up a
lot um and also like we had at some
point um code completion running with a
local model and then we could actually
serve 200 deaths for 200 watt with a
gaming engine so that's really
interesting um but will AI so all of
your problems like duct tape if it can't
fix it with duct tape then you have to
be using more well it seems like it
right uh with duct tape as well you can
use it to paint cars to make a nice bra
to fix airplanes and even to do
parenting but in the end um AI or duct
tape is still not the solution to every
problem so choose your um applications
wise there are a lot of things like
linters that do a great job without
having to use AI in there so um let's
have a look at the future outlook are we
out of job so I have this little H graph
here in white you can see everything
that humans can do in Black everything
that machines can automate or could
automate so you would say oh this white
space becomes smaller and smaller if
machines take over a lot of our work but
very interestingly what's been happening
throughout history and will happen now
again is that when humans and machines
combined they can do a lot more things
and there will always be this field
outside of what was possible before for
example we're developers most of us our
work would not be possible without
machines at all so I'm pretty sure with
AI this is gonna happen again like that
another interesting trend is that
throughout uh the existence of computers
and um software engineering we have seen
a lot of evolutions and revolutions that
made it much faster to code like uh
compilers high level languages
Frameworks and so you would think okay
we can code faster and faster we will be
out of jobs but now what we've seen is
actually the opposite Trend uh the world
seems to not have uh had enough software
developments yet until now so we expect
that this trend is going to
continue so that was it I hope uh you
got inspired to start trying out a few
things in your daily work um if you want
to reach out CH to me with great ideas
uh let me know and then I wish you all
goodbye see you in the
Q&A hello and joining me now is Lisa
Lisa welcome to AI native Devcon hi so
thank you for first of all for the
amazing presentation it's lovely to see
the the the Practical nature of of AI uh
AI coding today um what I'd love to
start off with actually uh in the video
and I think you've you you may have uh
adapted your um your presentation um
from the recording actually uh people
are mentioning swim in in the comments
um Thomas mentioned swim um oops in
terms of um swim uh you've had to play
with swim much yeah exactly I was
informed um so I had to play with it um
before I made a recording but yeah sadly
I didn't get to present live due to some
pregnancy complications I'm happy to be
here now um yeah so I played run with
swim uh it's very nice so it can
autogenerate documentation which was one
of my like dream checkboxes um it can
also auto sync your documentation and
that's that I find amazing when you
change your code it's G to update your
documentation I mean even interestingly
I think that if you do something stupid
in your code you will re see it
reflected in your documentation like as
bu fix like oops no that was not I
intended I love I love the connection as
well between the documentation and your
code so you know when you're in your ID
you can see the swim documentation which
is available for that code which I
absolutely love we've got a couple only
a couple minutes left but I'd love to
cover a couple of questions if we may um
Macy asks do you have a favorite ID
agnostic AI integration um because
everyone loves their IDE right so it's a
big ask to kind of leave the ID that you
you favor to go to a a vs vs code Fork
any thoughts exactly yeah I struggled
with the same thing that's why I copy it
back and forth um so um as far as I know
not there is Devo Jenny which is being
ported currently to vs code from uh
intell uh apart from that not that I
know I was actually Googling around for
it a bit and they're all very tied to an
IDE um maybe kodum and codium which are
two different tools may be better but
then again I must say like the quality
of cursor that's what does it for me
like just going over all the files in
one one go yeah that's why I go to vs
code even if I'm not that um fluent in
there because I guess I because Fork vs
code as well and they're probably so
deeply integrated into vs code it's
going to be super hard for them I guess
to Port onto other onto other IDs but
we'll we'll see I guess yeah I hope they
they do Port it at some point I saw they
raised some money so maybe they get the
the hands to do this yeah yeah
absolutely um another question from
Leslie how do you manage evaluations of
prompts within your Naboo
product um at the moment we've set up a
kind of benchmarking internally um with
a lot of chat GPT generating a lot of
fake documents over a lot of tools and
integration so it was quite a bit of
work um and then you can either do human
evaluation or let an llm evaluate or do
um keyword uh check a bit like as you
would evaluate every AI answer these
days yeah cool cool uh we have Patrick
who's asking he just wants more air time
see he's he's up next uh but we'll we'll
we'll we'll let him ask this question
how do you see the importance of tests
with all this automation
um I think like if you're speaking about
tests like unit test test coverage they
become very important if you want to
rely a lot on AI to write your code um
then your tests become a bit of your um
security against bugs because it's
indeed the the models themselves they're
not very secure uh they can produce bugs
so like test driven design plus AI
generated code is a really nice combo
again I also like to generate both the
tests and the code with thei and somehow
the the the issues pop up you have to
already be very unlucky that your wrong
tests validates your wrong piece of code
exactly in that way and then you would
miss it but that's very rare amazing
well Lisa I'm so happy you were able to
join us all the best for the coming days
and thank you so so much for joining us
on the a native Devcon and appreciate
your session wonderful session thank you
very much thank you very much